Hello, everyone. I'm Pornpat from DevForward, a software engineer.
สวัสดีครับทุกคน ผมพรพัฒน์ จาก DevForward เป็น Software Engineer ครับ
Sorry for technical difficulties.
ขออภัยในความไม่สะดวกทางเทคนิคด้วยนะครับ
Okay. Next slide.
โอเค สไลด์ต่อไปครับ
Okay. Usually, if you want to make a mobile application or desktop application, you have that note, right?
ปกติแล้ว ถ้าคุณต้องการสร้างแอปพลิเคชันมือถือหรือเดสก์ท็อป คุณต้องมีส่วนนี้ใช่ไหมครับ
In this case, it's a real project.
ในกรณีนี้ เป็นโปรเจกต์จริง
So in this case, I use Flutter.
ในกรณีนี้ ผมใช้ Flutter
The second thing you have to think about is the backend.
สิ่งที่สองที่คุณต้องคิดคือ backend
You have to make some API.
คุณต้องสร้าง API
So Supabase may be the answer.
ดังนั้น Supabase อาจเป็นคำตอบ
Yeah, you prepare to use this one.
ใช่ คุณเตรียมที่จะใช้ Supabase
The expectation is you have, you would like to request something via API from the database.
สิ่งที่คาดหวังคือ คุณต้องการดึงข้อมูลบางอย่างผ่าน API จาก database
But in this case, you have the legacy one.
แต่ในกรณีนี้ คุณมีระบบเดิม
I mean, the legacy system, like a report system.
ผมหมายถึง ระบบเดิม เช่น ระบบรายงาน
Next slide, ครับ.
สไลด์ต่อไปครับ
This one is like a traditional module.
นี่เป็นเหมือนโมดูลแบบดั้งเดิม
Someone in the company made it a long time ago, and it's still useful.
มีคนในบริษัทสร้างมันขึ้นมาเมื่อนานมาแล้ว และมันยังคงมีประโยชน์อยู่
So in this case, this module already exists, but the new one is not yet.
ดังนั้น ในกรณีนี้ โมดูลนี้มีอยู่แล้ว แต่โมดูลใหม่ยังไม่มี
So I would like to use Supabase in this case.
ดังนั้น ผมอยากจะใช้ Supabase ในกรณีนี้
Yeah, yeah, yeah. In this case, yeah.
ใช่ ใช่ ใช่ ในกรณีนี้ ใช่
So, some people think you can use this architecture.
บางคนคิดว่าคุณสามารถใช้สถาปัตยกรรมนี้ได้
You mean, if you want, for example, master data, you request via the first API.
ก็คือถ้าคุณต้องการ master data ก็ร้องขอผ่าน API แรก
And if you want to do some report or get the report file, you call the second API.
และถ้าคุณต้องการสร้างไฟล์รายงาน ก็เรียก API ที่สอง
You can do this, but for the authentication, privilege, you have to control about this.
คุณสามารถทำได้ แต่สำหรับการ authentication การกำหนดสิทธิ์ต่างๆ คุณต้องควบคุมสิ่งนี้
In this case, I try to merge them together.
ในกรณีนี้ ผมพยายามรวมเข้าด้วยกัน
This one already runs on DirectAdmin.
ระบบนี้ทำงานบน DirectAdmin อยู่แล้ว
It is an existing system.
มันเป็นระบบที่มีอยู่แล้ว
So my solution is to merge two things together and set them to seamlessly work together.
ดังนั้น วิธีแก้ปัญหาของผมคือการรวมสองสิ่งเข้าด้วยกัน และตั้งค่าให้ทำงานร่วมกันอย่างราบรื่น
This is the point.
นี่คือประเด็น
So, next slide, ครับ.
ดังนั้น สไลด์ต่อไปครับ
Okay, this one came to this picture.
โอเค มาถึงรูปนี้
So, for a mobile application, desktop application, or whatever application, you can get the master data or other things via Supabase.
สำหรับแอปพลิเคชันมือถือ แอปพลิเคชันเดสก์ท็อป หรือแอปพลิเคชันใดๆ คุณสามารถรับ master data หรือสิ่งอื่นๆ ผ่าน Supabase
And you can also make the edge function and call the edge function via Supabase.
และคุณยังสามารถสร้าง edge function และเรียก edge function ผ่าน Supabase ได้
And you can use the Supabase features, like JWT authentication, as you know from the previous talk.
และคุณสามารถใช้ฟีเจอร์ Supabase เช่น JWT authentication ได้อย่างที่คุณได้เรียนรู้ในหัวข้อก่อนหน้านี้
And also, you can keep the legacy system behind the scenes.
และคุณยังสามารถเก็บระบบเดิมไว้เบื้องหลังได้
So to do this, we will set up a little bit.
ในการทำเช่นนี้ เราจะตั้งค่าเล็กน้อย
The first one, we have a server for the DirectAdmin already.
อย่างแรก เรามีเซิร์ฟเวอร์สำหรับ DirectAdmin อยู่แล้ว
So the two things we have to do are, first, install Docker into the DirectAdmin server.
ดังนั้น สองสิ่งที่เราต้องทำคือ อย่างแรก ติดตั้ง Docker ลงในเซิร์ฟเวอร์ DirectAdmin
And also, you use Docker Compose to install Supabase.
และคุณใช้ Docker Compose เพื่อติดตั้ง Supabase
It's easy if you follow the steps on the website.
มันง่ายถ้าคุณทำตามขั้นตอนบนเว็บไซต์
Next, ครับ.
ต่อไปครับ
Yeah, you have to do two things.
ใช่ คุณต้องทำสองสิ่ง
Okay. This one I copied from the Supabase documentation.
โอเค อันนี้ผมคัดลอกมาจากเอกสารประกอบของ Supabase
So you just follow this one.
ดังนั้น คุณเพียงแค่ทำตามนี้
The first one, just go to your DirectAdmin server, I mean, your VM server.
อย่างแรก เพียงไปที่เซิร์ฟเวอร์ DirectAdmin ของคุณ ผมหมายถึง เซิร์ฟเวอร์ VM ของคุณ
Then you clone the repo of Supabase.
จากนั้นคุณ clone repo ของ Supabase
Second, you go to the Docker folder, you copy the environment file, and follow the documentation suggestions, for example, the private key.
ประการที่สอง คุณไปที่โฟลเดอร์ Docker คุณคัดลอกไฟล์ environment และทำตามคำแนะนำในเอกสารประกอบ ตัวอย่างเช่น private key
And the last two things, just Docker Compose pull and turn Docker up.
และสิ่งสุดท้าย เพียงแค่ Docker Compose pull และ Docker up
Okay, next.
โอเค ต่อไป
From this point, you will get everything that Supabase can do via this, following this API.
จากจุดนี้ คุณจะได้รับทุกสิ่งที่ Supabase สามารถทำได้ผ่าน API นี้
The dashboard, you can access via your IP and the port 8,000.
dashboard คุณสามารถเข้าถึงได้ผ่าน IP ของคุณและพอร์ต 8000
You can access the dashboard.
คุณสามารถเข้าถึง dashboard ได้
And another API, for example, the REST API for connecting to the database, authentication, storage, real-time.
และ API อื่นๆ ตัวอย่างเช่น REST API สำหรับการเชื่อมต่อกับ database การ authentication การจัดเก็บข้อมูล real-time
And also, the last one is function.
และสุดท้ายคือ function
If you write an edge function and put it into the Supabase volume, you can call the local function via Supabase API also.
ถ้าคุณเขียน edge function และใส่ไว้ใน volume ของ Supabase คุณสามารถเรียก local function ผ่าน Supabase API ได้เช่นกัน
Okay. And this one is where DirectAdmin comes to help.
โอเค และนี่คือจุดที่ DirectAdmin เข้ามาช่วย
Because DirectAdmin can control the config file.
เพราะ DirectAdmin สามารถควบคุมไฟล์ config ได้
Because this one already exists, so I use DirectAdmin to modify nginx, that connects the Supabase API and DirectAdmin API.
เพราะอันนี้มีอยู่แล้ว ดังนั้น ผมจึงใช้ DirectAdmin เพื่อแก้ไข nginx ที่เชื่อมต่อ Supabase API และ DirectAdmin API
So this one is a script, but it's very simple.
นี่คือสคริปต์ แต่มันง่ายมาก
You just see the two things.
คุณเพียงแค่ดูสองสิ่ง
The first thing, you just map the location of each API of Supabase.
สิ่งแรก คุณเพียงแค่ map ตำแหน่งของแต่ละ API ของ Supabase
And then you forward everything to Kong.
แล้วคุณ forward ทุกอย่างไปที่ Kong
Kong is here, it's on the 8,000 port.
Kong อยู่ที่นี่ มันอยู่บนพอร์ต 8000
So you do this.
ดังนั้น คุณทำเช่นนี้
So it means you can call everything from the Supabase API already.
ซึ่งหมายความว่าคุณสามารถเรียกทุกอย่างจาก Supabase API ได้แล้ว
But this one is especially for the legacy one.
แต่อันนี้เป็นพิเศษสำหรับระบบเดิม
You just remap it a bit.
คุณเพียงแค่ remap มันเล็กน้อย
Yeah. Next.
ใช่ ต่อไป
Okay. So the big picture is here.
โอเค ภาพรวมอยู่ที่นี่
Right. So, usually, DirectAdmin can control this one.
ใช่ ปกติแล้ว DirectAdmin สามารถควบคุมอันนี้ได้
It's very legacy.
มันเป็นระบบเดิม
But it's very easy if you want to make a sub-website or sub-system.
แต่มันง่ายมากถ้าคุณต้องการสร้าง sub-website หรือ sub-system
It's a very traditional one, a very traditional way.
คุณจะทำเป็นเว็บโฮสติ้งด้วยวิธีแบบดั้งเดิมก็ได้
But this one is the new one, that we connect previously.
แต่อันนี้เป็นแบบใหม่ ที่เราเชื่อมต่อก่อนหน้านี้
ครับ. Okay. Now, you can connect to Supabase with the domain name because basically Supabase provides only the IP address, you can access it via IP address.
ครับ โอเค ตอนนี้ คุณสามารถเชื่อมต่อกับ Supabase ด้วยชื่อโดเมนได้ เพราะโดยพื้นฐานแล้ว Supabase ให้เฉพาะที่อยู่ IP คุณสามารถเข้าถึงได้ผ่านที่อยู่ IP
But when you configure it this way, you can connect Supabase via the domain because DirectAdmin will manage the domains, DNS and HTTPS.
แต่เมื่อคุณกำหนดค่าด้วยวิธีนี้ คุณสามารถเชื่อมต่อ Supabase ผ่านโดเมนได้ เพราะ DirectAdmin จะจัดการโดเมน DNS และ HTTPS
And also, it forwards everything to Supabase containers.
และยัง forward ทุกอย่างไปยัง container ของ Supabase
So you can access it, and then you can see the dashboard here.
ดังนั้น คุณสามารถเข้าถึงได้ และคุณสามารถเห็น dashboard ที่นี่
And next.
และต่อไป
So, this one is an edge function because you want to call the report generator.
นี่คือ edge function เพราะคุณต้องการเรียกตัวสร้างรายงาน
It's a PDF file.
มันเป็นไฟล์ PDF
But the PDF file should be behind the Supabase API.
แต่ไฟล์ PDF ควรอยู่เบื้องหลัง Supabase API
So in this one, we write a small script to receive the request via Supabase and then pass it to the legacy system.
ดังนั้น ในอันนี้ เราเขียนสคริปต์ขนาดเล็กเพื่อรับคำขอผ่าน Supabase แล้วส่งต่อไปยังระบบเดิม
Like this.
แบบนี้
So this one is how you call the legacy one, normally.
นี่คือวิธีที่คุณเรียกระบบเดิมตามปกติ
And then you pass, maybe the authorization header, to the legacy one.
แล้วคุณส่ง header authorization ไปยังระบบเดิม
And then, if the legacy response is not 200, next slide, ครับ.
และถ้าการตอบสนองของระบบเดิมไม่ใช่ 200 — สไลด์ต่อไปครับ
You just pass everything back as the response.
คุณเพียงแค่ส่งทุกอย่างกลับเป็นการตอบสนอง
So in this way you can request the PDF file via Supabase API also.
ด้วยวิธีนี้ คุณสามารถร้องขอไฟล์ PDF ผ่าน Supabase API ได้เช่นกัน
Everything looks like it's via Supabase.
ทุกอย่างดูเหมือนว่าจะเรียกใช้งานผ่าน Supabase
You cannot see the API behind the scenes.
คุณไม่สามารถเข้าถึง API เบื้องหลังได้ตรงๆ
Okay. And this one is an application, or mobile application, that displays on the mobile or application.
โอเค และนี่คือแอปพลิเคชัน หรือแอปพลิเคชันมือถือ ที่แสดงบนมือถือหรือแอปพลิเคชัน
Yeah, the employee uses it.
ใช่ พนักงานใช้มัน
And then this one is the report.
และนี่คือรายงาน
If you call the API for the mobile application, you will get the PDF file.
ถ้าคุณเรียก API สำหรับแอปพลิเคชันมือถือ คุณจะได้รับไฟล์ PDF
And you don't need to care about the logic here because of the legacy system.
และคุณไม่จำเป็นต้องสนใจระบบเบื้องหลังที่เชื่อมต่อกับระบบเดิมนี้เลย
You just pass the ID or information through it.
คุณเพียงแค่ส่ง ID หรือข้อมูลที่จำเป็นให้มันก็พอ
Yeah. This is it.
ใช่ แค่นี้แหละ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณครับ